A Guide to the Norfolk County (Va.), Lists of Tithables and Taxable Property, 1732-1783.
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Norfolk County (Va.), List of Tithables and Taxable Property, 1732-1783.
The Library of Virginia
1161800-1161805, 0007686900
6 boxes (3.00 cu. ft.).
Chesapeake (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This item came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from City of Chesapeake Circuit Court. A portion of the collection was transferred to Library of Virginia under the accession number 42982.
Alternative Form Available
See Barcode number 1114824.
Historical Information
Norfolk County was formed from Lower Norfolk County in 1691. Now extinct, Norfolk County was incorporated into the city of Chesapeake in 1963.
In seventeenth- and eighteenth-century Virginia, the term "tithable" referred to a person who paid (or for whom someone else paid) one of the taxes imposed by the General Assembly for the support of civil government in the colony. In colonial Virginia, a poll tax or capitation tax was assessed on free white males, African American slaves, and Native American servants (both male and female), all age sixteen or older. Owners and masters paid the taxes levied on their slaves and servants. For a more detailed history of tithables, consult "Colonial tithables" research note found on the Library of Virginia's web site.
Scope and Content
Norfolk County (Va.) Lists of Tithables and Taxable Property, 1732-1783. Consists of manuscript lists of tithable heads of household in the county for the years 1732 through 1781 and taxable property lists for 1782 and 1783. Information recorded includes name of head of hosehold, name of slave owners, and names of enslved people. Also included are loose and partial lists of tithables. The former were used to compile the final lists. The loose and partial lists are arranged at the end of each box.
A donation to the Library of Virginia's Adopt Virginia's History program by the National Society Daughters of the Barons of Runnemede has helped to fund the conservation for Norfolk Tithables, Norfolk County, Virginia, 1745-1777 (Barcode number 0007686900).
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically in each box with loose and partial lists placed at the end.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Chesapeake (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
Slaves -- Virginia -- Norfolk County.; Taxation -- Virginia -- Norfolk County.
Geographical Names:
Chesapeake (Va.) -- History.; Norfolk County (Va.) -- History -- 18th century.
Genre and Form Terms:
Local government records -- Virginia -- Norfolk County.; Tax and fiscal records -- Virginia -- Norfolk County.; Tithable lists -- Virginia -- Norfolk County.
Added Entry - Corporate Name:
Norfolk County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Contents List
- From West Side of the Southern Branch from Suggs Mill to Batcheldors, by Willis Wilson, 1732 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- On the West Side of the Southern Branch, by Willis Wilson, 1733 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Unidentified District, Enumerator, [1733] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Ferry Point to Great Bridge, by Nathaniel Tatum, 1734 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- From Suggs Mill to Deepe Creek, by Willis Wilson, 1734 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- On Tanner's Creek, by Solomon Wilson, 1734 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Above the Bridge, by Thomas Wright, 1734 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Four Southern Branch From Deep Creek to West Branch, by Thomas Scott, 1734 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- From Ferry Point to the Great Bridge, by Captain Tatum, 1735 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- From South Side of Southern Branch from head of Deep Creek to Col. Craford's, 1735 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- From Above The Bridge, by Thomas Wright, 1735 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- From Ferry Point to the Great Bridge, by Captain Tatum, 1736 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- In The Borough of Norfolk and the Southern Side of Daniel Tanner's Creek, by Christopher Perkins, 1750 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- In The Borough of Norfolk and the South Side of Tanner's Creek and to Spratt's Bridge, 1753 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- From Portsmouth to Batcheldors, by William Craford, 1757 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- In The Borough of Norfolk South Side of Tanner's Creek and to Spratt's Bridge, by Josiah Smith, 1757 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- From Great Bridge to Edmond's Bridge and Batcheldor's Mill, by James Webb, 1757 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- From the Northside of Tanner's Creek, by Matthew Godfrey, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Borough of Norfolk South Side of Tanner's Creek to Great Bridge, by Josiah Smith, 1759 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- From Edmond's Bridge to the Upper Inhabitants of Norfolk County- St. Brides Parish, by Samuel Happer, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- From Great Bridge to Edmond's Bridge and North Mill Creek, by James Webb, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- South Side of Tanner's Creek as far as Willis Care's on the North Side of the Said Creek, by Matthew Godfrey, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- For East Division of the Borough of Norfolk, by J. Hutchings, 1765 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- List of Tithables, Land and Carriages for the East Division of the Borough of Norfolk, by Joseph Hutchings, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- On the South Side of Tanner's Creek as far as Willis Care's on the North Side of the Said Creek and to Extent of the Bounds of the County, by Matthew Godfrey, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- List of Tithables, Land and Carriages in St. Brides Parish from Edmond's Bridge to the Upper Inhabitants Including Both Roads, by Samuel Happer, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- From the Great Bridge to Edmund's Bridge and New Mill Creek, by James Webb, 1766 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- From Edmund's Bridge to the Upper Inhabitants of Norfolk County- St. Brides Parish, by Samuel Hopper, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge and Northwest Creek, by James Webb, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- On South Side of Tanner's Creek as far as Willis Carey and to the Extent of the Bounds of the County by Samuel Godfrey, 1767 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- St. Brides Parish Great Bridge Division, by John Wilson, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- James Campbell's Company, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- St. Brides Parish from Edmund's Bridge Including Both Roads to the Upper Inhabitants, by Malachi Wilson, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- [Unidentified], by Matthew Godfrey, 1768 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- On the South Side of the Western Branch Precinct Parish of Portsmouth, by Thomas Veale, 1769 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- From Edmunds Bridge tot he Upper Inhabitants Including Both Roads, by Samuel Happer, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- [Unidentified], by David Porter, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- [Unidentified], by Thomas Veale, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- [Unidentified], by David Porter, 1772 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- On the...Side of Willoughby's Land and West Side of Church Street as far as the Bounds of the Said Borough, by Joseph..., 1772 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- South Side of Tanner's Creek as far as Care's on the North Side of Tanners Creek to the Bounds of the County, 1772 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- [Unidentified], 1772 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- From Edmonds Bridge to the Upper Inhabitants of Norfolk County- St. Brides Parish Including Both Roads, by Samuel Happer, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- On the North Side of Tanner's Creek, by Matthew Godfrey, 1773 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- [Loose Tithables to be added to lists of Hutchings, Newton, Murphree, Portlock, Tatem], 1773 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- [Unidentified], by David Porter, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- On the Eastern Side of the Western Branch, John Brickell, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- From Edmunds Bridge to the Upper Inhabitants of the Norfolk County- St. Brides Parish Including Both Roads, by Samuel Happer, 1774 (Box 1, Folder 48)
- North Side of Tanners Creek, by John Willoughby, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 49)
- On the Southside of the Western Branch from Portsmouth to Halls Mill, by Samuel Veale, 1780 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- List of Tithables for the South Side of Tanners Creek as far as Willis Care's on the Northside of Said Creek and to the Extent of the County, by Matthew Godfrey, 1781 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- List to Tithables from Great Bridge to Edmunds Bridge and to New Mill Creek, by Daniel Sanford, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Loose Tithables, 1770 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- Individual Tithable Lists Intended for Inclusion on Master List, 1778 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Individual Tithable Lists Intended for Inclusion on Master List, 1771 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- Individual Tithable Lists Intended for Inclusion on Master List, 1767, 1770, 1774, 1798, undated (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Partial Lists, 1773-1774 and undated (Box 1, Folder 57)
- Loose Tithable Lists to Add to Final List, 1769 and undated (Box 1, Folder 58)
- List of Enumerated Articles [Partial], by Malachi Wilson, 1782 (Box 1, Folder 59)
- Envelopes Which Held Tithable Lists, Various (Box 1, Folder 60)
- From William Craford's to the Head of Deep Creek, by Thomas Scott, 1732 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Tanners Creek, 1735 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- From Suggs Mill to Batcheldors Mill, by Willis Wilson, 1735 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- From Deep Creek to the Bridge and From Bridge to Northwest Landing, 1736 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Borough of Norfolk and Northside of Tanners Creek to Spratts Bridge, by Josiah Smith, 1752 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- On the Western Side of the Southern Branch from Batcheldors Mill, by George Veale, 1753 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Western District, by George Veale, 1757 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- [Unidentified], by Thomas Veale, 1759 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- From Edmunds Bridge Up Pocaty and to Northwest Roads, by Robert Tucker, 1759 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- From Portsmouth to Western Branch, by John Tatem, 1761 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- In Portsmouth Parish on the Westside of the Western Branch, by John Tatem, 1767 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- From Great Bridge to Edmunds Bridge to New Mill Creek, by James Webb, 1770 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge to New Mill Creek, by Daniel Sanford, 1732 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Town of Portsmouth to New Mill Creek, by Paul Loyall, 1780 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- On the South Side of the Western Branch and from there to New Mill Creek, by William Booker, 1782 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- [Unidentified], by Malachi Wilson, 1782 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- List of Tithables from Ferry Point to Great Bridge, by Samuel Veale, 1782 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Borough of Norfolk [Partial], by Joseph Hutchings, 1760s (Box 2, Folder 18)
- [Unidentified Partial List], undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- [Unidentified Partial List], Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- [Unidentified Partial List], 1774 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Of Indian Creek, 1732 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- List From Suggs Mill to the Great Bridge and Up Both Roads, by James Wilson, 1732 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- For the Western Branch, by Thomas Scott 1732 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- For Indian Creek, by Samuel Boush, 1733 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- From Suggs Mill to the Great Bridge and Up Both Roads, by James Wilson, 1733 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- From Suggs Mill to the Great Bridge and So Up Both Roads, by James Wilson, 1733 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- For Indian Creek Canton, by Samuel Boush, 1733 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- On the Western Branch, by Thomas Scott, 1733 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- From the Hollow Poplar Down to the Great Bridge and to Batcheldor and Up Poakley Road, by Joshua Corprew, 1750 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- From the Hollow Poplar to the Upper Inhabitants, by Joseph Stewart, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- From Great Bridge to Ferry Point, by Markcom Herbert, 1752 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- From the Hollow Poplar Down to the Great Bridge and Up Pocoty Road and Down to Batcheldors Mill, by Joseph Corprew, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Between Ferry Point and the Great Bridge, by William Portlock, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- For the Western Branch, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- On the North Side of Tanners Creek, by John Willoughby, 1753 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- From the Great Bridge to the Ferry Point, by Robert Jackson, 1757 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge to Batcheldors Bridge, by Joshua Corprew, 1759 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- In the Southern Branch, by Thomas Veale, 1761 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge to New Mill Creek in St Brides Parish, by Joshua Corprew, 1761 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- East Division of the Borough of Norfolk, by John Tatem, 1767 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- On the South Side of Western Branch, by Thomas Veale, 1768 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- On the North Side of the Western Branch, by John Tatem, 1770 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- In the East Division of the Borough of Norfolk, by John Taylor, 1770 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- For North Side of Tanners Creek, 1770 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- On the North Side of the Western Branch, by John Tatem, 1773 (Box 3, Folder 25)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge and New Mill Creek, by William Smith, 1777 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge and to New Mill Creek, by Daniel Sanford, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- From Ferry Point to the Great Bridge, by Thomas Nash, 1778 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- For the Borough of Norfolk on the South Side of Tanners Creek as far as Willis Care's on the North Side of Said Creek and to the Bounds of the County, by Matthew Godfrey, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- [List], by Malachi Wilson, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- On the North Side of the Western Branch on the Nansemond Line, by William Booker, 1778 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- South Side of Tanners Creek, by Bassett Moseley, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- North Side of Tanners Creek, by John Tabb, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- From Ferry Point to the Great Bridge, by Thomas Nash, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- [List],by Malachi Wilson, 1780 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- List of Those Who Omitted Giving Their Taxable Property for 1782, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- List of Taxable Property (Tithes, Slaves, Horses, Cattle), by Charles Conner, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- On the North Side of the Western Branch, by Charles Conner, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 38)
- On the North Side of Tanners Creek from Samuel Godfrey's to Sewalls Point, by John Tabb, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- List of Articles Subject to Tax on the North Side of Tanners Creek, by John Tabb, 1782 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- ...For the Western Branch, by Thomas Scott, 1734 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- From Western Side of the Southern Branch from Batcheldors Mill Down, 1736 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Taken in the Western Branch [Precinct], by George Veale, 1750 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- List of the Western Side of the Southern Branch, by George Veale, 1752 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- From the Hollow Poplar to the Upper Inhabitants, by William Bradley, 1753 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- [Unidentified District], by Joshua Corprew, 1756 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- From Batcheldors Creek to Portsmouth, by Will Craford, 1756 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- From Edmonds Bridge to the Upper Inhabitants and Up to Poakety Bridge, 1757 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- For the North Side of Tanners Creek, by Charles Sweny, 1757 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- From Ferry Point to Great Bridge, by James Webb, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Western Branch District, by George Veale, 1759 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- From Edmonds Bridge Including Both Roads to the Upper Inhabitants, by Robert Tucker, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Beginning at Willoughbys Lane Running Up the Western Side of Church Street to Town Bridge, by Maxmillian Calvert; [Unidentified District], by Lemuel Willoughby, 1761 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- From the Ferry Point to the Great Bridge, James Webb, 1762 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- In the Western District of Norfolk Borough, by William Aitchison, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 15)
- On the North Side of Tanners Creek, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 16)
- From Ferry Point to the Great Bridge, by John Portlock, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- From Portsmouth to New...[Mill Creek], by George Veale, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- [Unidentified District], by John Tatem, 1765 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- [List of Tithables], by Thomas Veale, 1766 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- From Portsmouth to New Mill Creek in the Southern Branch Precinct, by George Veale, 1766 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- List of Tithables, Wheeled Carriages and Quantity of Land on the North Side of Tanners Creek, by William Ivey, 1766 (Box 5, Folder 3)
- On the South Side of the Western Branch District, by Thomas Veale, 1767 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- In Norfolk Borough on the East Side of the Church Street Beginning on the West Side of Willoughby Deceased Lane and Running Up Church Street to the Extent of the Bounds of the Borough, 1767 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Town of Portsmouth and Southern Branch Precinct, 1767 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- On the North Side of Tanners Creek, by William Ivy, 1767 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- [List of Tithables], by John Portlock, 1768 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- In Portsmouth Parish on the Western Side of the Western Branch, by John Tatem, 1768 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- On the North Side of Tanners Creek, by William Ivy, Sr., 1768 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- In Elizabeth River Parish, by Thomas Newton, Jr., 1768 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- From Portsmouth to New Mill Creek, by David Porter, 1768 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- From Great Bridge to Ferry Point, by John Portlock, 1769 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- For the West Division of Norfolk Borough, by Cornelius Calvert, 1770 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- On the South Side of the Tanners Creek as far as Willis Care's on the North Side of the Said Creek and to the Extent of the Bounds of Norfolk County, by William Aitchison, 1770 (Box 5, Folder 15)
- From the Great Bridge to the Ferry Point, by John Portlock, 1770 (Box 5, Folder 16)
- For North Side of Tanners Creek, by Matthew Phripp, 1772 (Box 5, Folder 17)
- From Great Bridge to the Ferry Point, by John Portlock, 1772 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- [Unidentified District, Unidentified Enumerator], 1772 (Box 5, Folder 19)
- On the South Side of the Western Branch District, by Thomas Veale, 1773 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- [Unidentified District], by John Wilson, 1773 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- In the Western Division of the Borough of Norfolk, by Thomas Newton, 1773 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- On the South Side of Tanners Creek, by William Aitcheson, 1773 (Box 6, Folder 4)
- In the Eastern Division of the Borough of Norfolk, by Joseph Hutchings, 1773 (Box 6, Folder 5)
- From Great Bridge to Edmonds Bridge and New Mill Creek, by James Webb, 1774 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- East Side of Church Street, by Bassett Moseley, 1774 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- On the North Side of Tanners Creek From the Land of Willis Care, by Arthur Banks, 1774 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Western Precinct of the Borough of Norfolk, by Robert Taylor, 1774 (Box 6, Folder 9)
- From Portsmouth to New Mill Creek, by Samuel Veale, 1778 (Box 6, Folder 10)
- From Portsmouth Along South Side of the Western Branch, by Thomas Veale, 1778 (Box 6, Folder 11)
- List of Taxable Property, by William Booker, 1782 (Box 6, Folder 12)
- List of Free Male Tithables, Slaves and Other Taxable Property on the South Side of Tanners Creek, by James Taylor, 1782 (Box 6, Folder 13)
- On the South Side of Tanners Creek, 1782 (Box 6, Folder 14)
- List of Tithables [Partial], Undated (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Tithable lists, 1744-1777 (Box 7)